Guide to the Bateman Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Bateman family papers
1756-1812
OSB MSS 32
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
Correspondence between family members. Includes letters between Rebekah Clegg Bateman and her husband, Thomas Bateman, her son, William Bateman, her father, Arthur Clegg, and her sister, Elizabeth Clegg Wilson; letters between Rebekah Bateman and her brothers, William and Thomas Bateman; one letter from Thomas Bateman to his son, Thomas; and letters between William Bateman and his brother, Thomas, and his father, Thomas. Many of the letters are written by and to children at school. Also included are hymns, poetry, prayers, and excerpts from sermons written down by Rebekah Clegg Bateman; and a travel diary written by her son, Thomas, about a visit to the Lake Country.
Bateman family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1974 from Myers, Ltd. for the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BATEMAN FAMILY CHART
NB: Limited to persons represented in the Bateman Family Papers.
Arthur Clegg (ca. 1732-1818) m. Sarah Pearson (ca. 1733-1811)
----Rebekah Clegg (1766-1797) m. 1786 Thomas Bateman (ca. 1765-1847)
--------William Bateman (1787-1835) m. Mary Crompton
------------Thomas Bateman (1821-1861) m. 1847 Sarah Parker
--------Thomas Bateman, Jr. (1791-1810)
--------Rebekah Bateman (b. 1794)
----Elizabeth Clegg m. 1791 Thomas Wilson (1764-1843)
--------Rebakah Wilson (b. 1792)
--------Joshua Wilson (1795-1874) m. 1837 Mary Wood
--------Elizabeth Wilson
WILLIAM BATEMAN (1787-1835)
William Bateman was the eldest son of Thomas Bateman, a Dissenting Manchester cotton merchant, and his wife Rebekah Clegg Bateman. He was apprenticed to and later joined his father in the cotton business, but by the early 1820s he retired to Middleton by Youlgrave in Derbyshire. A Fellow of the Society of Antiquaries, Bateman undertook several excavations of barrows and tumuli in the Peak district, publishing notes on these in the Archaeologia. Some of his dig notes were arranged and published by his son Thomas, who was also an amateur archaeologist, in C. R. Smith's Collectanea Antiqua. Bateman died on June 11, 1835.
Scope and Contents
The Bateman Family Papers consist of correspondence and related material connected to the family of Thomas Bateman of Manchester. The papers span the dates 1756-1818, and have been arranged alphabetically by author. They were apparently selected, bound, and annotated by William Bateman (1787-1835) around 1818, and later partially disbound. Papers relating to his brother Thomas Bateman, Jr., who died of "water on the brain" in 1810 at the age of 18, had been previously gathered and annotated by Thomas Bateman (ca. 1765-1847).
Thomas Bateman and his wife, Rebekah Clegg Bateman, were fervent Dissenters, and their correspondence both with each other and with other family members reflects their strong interest in religious matters. Many letters contain reports of sermons, prayer sessions, meditations on Bible verses, self-examinations and exhortations to lead a Christian life. Other topics include family news, discussions of health and schooling for the children, arrangements for travel and visits, and errands to be done while Thomas is in London or Manchester on business.
The letters of Elizabeth Clegg Wilson to her sister Rebekah are particularly strong in reports of church and chapel events; news of neighbors, fellow church members, and distant relatives; and analyses of her personal spiritual state. Elizabeth was particularly concerned with the quality of local ministers, and they did not all meet with her approval; in 1796 she noted of "Mr. Lindal" that "I wish he would give up preaching and go to his weaving or whatever was his trade."
Rebekah Clegg Bateman's own religious concerns are documented in the collection of her miscellaneous papers located in Box 2, folder 12. These include her "Parts" for Sabbath Day exercises; copies of prayers and hymns; and inspirational quotations from sermons.
The letters exchanged among the younger Bateman and Wilson cousins contain school and family news, humorous comments on presents and upcoming family visits, and occasional mentions of parental finances and business conditions. Thomas Bateman's 1809 letters to his brother William describe his walking tour of the Lake District and his reaction to a Fourth of July celebration by American sailors in Liverpool which was disrupted by British carpenters. Further description of his Lake District tour, as well as other personal papers, a pencil portrait of him, and accounts of his illness and death, can be be found in folders 16-18. A copy of his funeral sermon, delivered by the Reverend Peter Samuel Charrier, is located in folder 22.
Brothers and sisters -- Great Britain; Children's writings; Fathers and daughters -- Great Britain; Fathers and sons -- Great Britain; Husband and wife -- Great Britain; Mothers and daughters -- Great Britain; Mothers and sons -- Great Britain; Diaries; Hymns (documents); Poetry; Prayers (documents); Sermons; Bateman, Rebekah Clegg, ca. 1763-1797; Bateman, Rebekah, b. ca. 1794; Bateman, Thomas, 1791-1810; Bateman, William, 1787-1835; Clegg, Arthur; Clegg, Sarah Pearson, ca. 1733-1811; Wilson, Elizabeth Clegg; Bateman family
- Bateman Family Papers, Series I
  - ALLWOOD, ANNA MARIA
    - 10 ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman; various places, 1789-[1791?] (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - ARMITAGE, WILLIAM
    - 2 ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman; Chester, 1790, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - BATEMAN, REBEKAH, B. CA. 1794
    - 8 ALS to Thomas Bateman, Jr.; various places, 1808-10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Scope and Contents
      Most of these letters also include
      notes to Thomas from cousin Rebecca
      Wilson.
    - 11 ALS and 1 AL to William Bateman; Islington and other places, 1806-09 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - BATEMAN, REBEKAH CLEGG, CA.1763-1797
    - 47 ALS to her husband Thomas Bateman; mostly from Manchester, 1786-97 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 2 ALS to her son William Bateman; Gatley, 1796, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Accompanied by copy of the 1797
      letter in William Bateman's hand,
      poem on "happy scenes of youth"
      dated "May 1818", and notes on
      his mother's death.
    - ALS to her father Arthur Clegg; Gatley, 1797 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      With 2 copies, annotated with
      information on "her sudden death
      at Gatley Hall"
    - 4 ALS to Margery Smithson; various places, 1780-97 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 20 ALS to Mary Jane Hodson Durdon Barclay Whitby; Manchester, etc., 1781-91 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Annotated by William Bateman
    - 3 ALS to her sister Elizabeth Clegg Wilson; various places, 1781-92 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts, 1777-91, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Includes devotional poetry, prayers,
      school exercises, excerpts from
      sermons, hymns, accounts,
      and medical prescriptions for
      William Bateman.
  - BATEMAN, THOMAS
    - 5 ALS to his son Thomas Bateman, Jr.; various places, 1808-10 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - BATEMAN, THOMAS, 1791-1810
    - ALS (draft?) to his sister Rebekah Bateman; Liverpool, 1810 Jan (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 16 ALS to his brother William Bateman; various places, 1809-10 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Accompanied by notes, a poem, and
      a pencil portrait of Thomas by
    - MS account of the final illness and death of Thomas Bateman, Jr, with notes on his "delirious conversation" and medical treatment, 1810 Apr 22 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Document, signed: indenture, 1807 Aug 31 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Apprenticing Thomas Bateman, Jr. to
      his father Thomas for seven years,
      to be taught "the business of a
      cotton merchant."
    - "Letters belonging to my late dear boy Thomas, found in his drawers May 1810", [ca. 1800-10] (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Letters and papers describing his
      1809 tour of the Lake District
      Bound with poems, school exercises,
      cash accounts, and other papers,
      and annotated by Thomas Bateman.
  - BATEMAN, WILLIAM, 1787-1835
    - ALS to (his father) Thomas Bateman; Pauls Cray [Kent], 1801 Jan 29 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 4 ALS to (his brother) Thomas Bateman, Jr.; Manchester, 1809-10 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - ALS to unidentified; Manchester, 1812 Mar 2 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - CHARRIER, PETER SAMUEL, CA. 1769-1826
    - Funeral sermon on the death of Thomas Bateman (1791-1810), holograph, 1810 May 6 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Sermon text is Psa. 102:23.
      Annotated by William Bateman.
  - CLEGG, ARTHUR, CA. 1732-1818
    - ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman and Elizabeth Clegg Wilson; Manchester, 1778 Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - CLEGG, SARAH PEARSON, CA. 1733-1811
    - 4 ALS to her daughter Rebekah Clegg Bateman; various places, 1778-96 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 5 ALS to her daughters Rebekah Clegg Bateman and Elizabeth Clegg Wilson; Manchester, 1777-78 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - HOPE, JOHN
    - ALS to Thomas Bateman, Jr.; Manchester, 1797 Jun 24 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Letter of condolence on the death
      of Rebekah Clegg Bateman.
  - HOWARD, OLIVE
    - ALS to the Rev. Mr. [?]; Stockport, 1756 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - HUNT, H.
    - ALS to [Arthur Clegg?], Delph, 1779 Feb 29 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Sending books to be studied by
      Clegg's daughters.
  - KELSO, SETH
    - ALS to Arthur Clegg; Portsmouth, 1796 Sep 22 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Docketed: "A letter from one of the
      Missionarys gone to South Sea
      Islands...." Religious sentiments.
  - PEARSON, JAMES, CA. 1737-1816
    - ALS to Elizabeth Clegg Wilson; Bolton, 1786 Jul 6 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - RUTT, ANN
    - ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman; Mile End, 1777 Dec 30 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - SIMPSON, M.
    - ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman, 1779 Sep 29 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - WHITBY, MARY JANE HODSON DURDON BARCLAY
    - 3 ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman; Chester, 1784-91 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - WILSON, ANN, CA. 1773-1822
    - ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman; Manchester, 1781 Apr 1 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - WILSON, ELIZABETH
    - 2 ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman; Manchester, 1780, 1781 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - WILSON, ELIZABETH CLEGG
    - 46 ALS to her sister Rebekah Clegg Bateman; various places, 1787-97 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Letterbook. Family news, religious
      discussion, comments on the Dissenting
      church at Manchester and elsewhere.
      Bound with printed portraits of
      several ministers mentioned in
      the letters.
    - 4 ALS to her brother-in-law Thomas Bateman, London, 1798-1801 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - ALS to Margery Smithson, London, n.y. May (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - WILSON, MARY, CA.1766-1830
    - 2 ALS to Rebekah Clegg Bateman; Highbury Place, 1792, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - WILSON, REBEKAH, B. CA. 1792
    - ALS to Thomas Bateman; Tyndale Place, 1810 Mar 13 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - WILSON, THOMAS, 1764-1843
    - ALS to Thomas Bateman; London, 1797 Jun 19 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Condolence letter on the death
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - Genealogical notes, bookplate, etc., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)